Finding aid to Eva Kollisch papers SSC.MS.00510
Sophia Smith Collection
Eva Kollisch papers
1942-2013
Sophia Smith Collection
Kollisch, Eva
SSC.MS.00510
5.854 linear feet (13 boxes)
Eva Berliner Kollisch (1925-) is an author and activist. She taught at Sarah Lawrence for thirty years, during which time she and Gerda Lerner and Joan Kelly created the Women's Studies Program. A significant portion of the collection pertains to Kollisch's years of teaching at Sarah Lawrence College, as well as to the writing and publication of her book, Girl in Movement: A Memoir(2002). Kollisch's interest in and involvement with several peace, disarmament, and anti-war organizations, notably the Women's Pentagon Action, is well-documented and includes extensive subject files.
Biographical Note
Eva Berliner Kollisch (1925-) is an author and activist. She was born in Vienna, Austria, the daughter of Margaret Moller and Otto Kollisch and escaped with her two younger brothers, Steven and Peter, to England in 1939 via Kindertransport, the organized rescue effort that facilitated the escape to England of some ten-thousand Jewish children from Austria, Czechoslovakia and Germany. Her parents also escaped andtThe family was reunited in April, 1940, in New York. Eva Kollisch graduated from Curtis High School in Staten Island, NY in 1942. That year she joined the Workers Party, a Trotskyist organization that sent its members into factories to radicalize the workers. She abandoned her plans for college and, from 1942 to 1945, worked and organized in sweatshops in New York City and in auto plants in Detroit. During this time she met and married a comrade, Stanley Plastric; she divorced in Plastric in 1946, at which time she also left the Workers Party. In 1948, Kollisch met Gert Berliner, a German Jewish refugee and artist, whom she married and with whom she had one child, Uri Berliner (b. 1956); they divorced in 1959. Kollisch earned her undergraduate degree from Brooklyn College in 1951, and her M.A. from Columbia University in 1963. She studied in the Ph.D. program at New York University but decided not to complete a dissertation. Kollisch taught Comparative Literature and German, first at Broooklyn College and, at Sarah Lawrence College for thirty years, during which time she and Gerda Lerner and Joan Kelly created the Women's Studies Program there. Since the 1960s, Kollisch has been involved in numerous political causes, including the peace movement, anti-war activism, nuclear disarmament, feminism, and gay and lesbian rights. She has written essays and stories for anthologies and magazines, and her book, Girl in Movement, was published in 2000. She lives in New York City with life-partner, poet Naomi Replansky.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use with following restrictions on access: At the donor's request, her diaries and journals are closed to researchers until her death.
Related Materials
Voices of Feminism Oral History Project
Scope and Contents
The Eva Kollisch papers consist of two series of materials. The first includes information about Kollisch's education, a small amount of financial information, documents pertaining to her apartment and to her country house in Middletown, New York, and materials relating to several trips to Europe. A significant portion of the accession pertains to Kollisch's years of employment at Sarah Lawrence College, as well as to the writing and publication of her book, Girl in Movement: A Memoir(2002). Kollisch's interest in and involvement with several peace, disarmament, and anti-war organizations, notably the Women's Pentagon Action, is well-documented and includes extensive subject files. Photographs of the Nov. 11, 2009 wedding of Kollish and Naomi Replansky are also included. The second series accession consists of correspondence, photographs, published and unpublished writings, reviews of her work and other clippings, as well as extensive journals.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Eva Kollisch.
Immigrants--United States--Biography--Sources; Jewish women--United States--Biography--Sources; Refugees, Jewish--Biography--Sources; Women socialists--United States--Biography--Sources; Working class women--United States--Biography--Sources; Address books; Appointment books; Catalogs; Deeds; Faculty papers; Fliers; Publications; Peace movements--History--20th century--Sources; Jewish women -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Brochures; articles; Nuclear disarmament -- History -- Sources; Financial records; Women and peace--History--20th century-Sources; Photographs.; Notes; correspondence; clippings; Kollisch, Eva, 1925-; Sarah Lawrence College--Faculty--Biography--Sources; Women's Encampment for a Future of Peace and Justice
- Eva Kollisch papers, 1942-2003; Accession 2004-S-0070
  Scope and Contents
  This accession consists of the first installment of the Eva Kollisch Papers and includes information about Kollisch's education, a small amount of financial information, documents pertaining to her apartment and to her country house in Middletown, New York, and materials relating to several trips to Europe. A significant portion of the accession pertains to Kollisch's years of employment at Sarah Lawrence College, as well as to the writing and publication of her book, Girl in Movement (2002). Kollisch's interest in and involvement with several peace, disarmament, and anti-war organizations, notably the Women's Pentagon Action, is well-documented and includes extensive subject files. There are also many newpaper clippings by journalist Uri Berliner, who is likely related to Kollisch.
  - Appointments books and calendars, 1972-2002; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Address book, 1972; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Photographs: Auschwitz Concentration Camp, 1998; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Photographs: Wedding to Naomi Replansky, 2009; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Financial information, 1971-2001; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Newspaper articles by Uri Berliner, 1980-1994; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Notes for Kollisch's M.A. and Ph.D. orals, 1964; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Subject files: clippings and articles, 1983-2003; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Employment at Sarah Lawrence College: Evaluations and recommendations, 1990-1992; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Employment at Sarah Lawrence College: Directories and publications, 1988-2001; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Employment at Sarah Lawrence College: Writings by students, 1990-1994; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1992-1994; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Academic and personnel issues involving Kollisch: correspondence, memoranda, and notes, 1977-1998; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Academic degrees and certificates, 1952-1964; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Contracts and related correspondence, 1961-1982; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Travel: brochures, maps, and itineraries, 1973-1996; 1 items (Box 3)
  - High school essays, 1942; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Subject files re: emigration (including the film, "The Rescue," about saving Danish Jews from the Nazis): pamphlets, brochures, clippings, and articles, 1995-2002; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Kindertransport Association: conference materials, 1998-2002; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Hospice: volunteer agreement, 1994; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Real estate holdings: correspondence, leases, deeds, and contracts, 1986-1999; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Legal and financial information, 2000; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Employment at Sarah Lawrence College: lecture notes and other teaching materials, evaluations, and student papers, 1977-1998; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Writings: Girl in Movement - Notes, clippings and articles for potential novel (probably Girl in Movement), 1978-1990; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Writings: Girl in Movement - Notes and emails re: German translation, 2002-2003; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Publication: notes, proofs, correspondence, press releases, and reviews, 2000-2003; 1 items (Box 5)
  - Kindertransport Association: newsletters and membership lists, 1991-1998; 1 items (Box 6)
  - Employment at Sarah Lawrence College: catalogs, student recommendations, and lecture notes, 1964; 1 items (Box 6)
  - Peace and nuclear disarmament: General clippings, brochures, publications, and fliers, 1981-1983; 1 items (Box 6)
  - Women's Pentagon Action - Women's Peace Encampment (Seneca, NY): clippings, correspondence, and fliers, 1983-1984; 1 items (Box 6)
  - March on New York: clippings, correspondence, fliers and posters, 1980-1982; 1 items (Box 7)
  - Biographical information about Uri Berliner, and newspaper articles by him, 1977-1989; 1 items (Box 7)
- Eva Kollisch papers addition, 1950-2013; 2013-S-0038
  This accession consists of correspondence, photographs, published and unpublished writings, reviews of her work and other clippings as well as extensive journals.
  - Articles and books by Eva Kollisch, 1992-2003 (Box 8)
  - Personal correspondence with grandson Ben Berliner and others, 1996-2011 (Box 8)
  - "Nana's stories", undated (Box 8)
  - Uri and Muffin Berliner correspondence, 1987-2006 (Box 8)
  - General correspondence, 1994-2010 (Box 8)
  - Gerald Ardito correspondence, 2003-2009 (Box 8)
  - General correspondence, 1984-2013 (Box 9)
  - Journals and notebooks, 1973-2010 (Box 10)
  - Typed journals, 2002-05-2012-12 (Box 11)
  - Excerpts from old travel journals, undated (Box 11)
  - Fragments, notes, and drafts, 1950-2010 (Box 11)
  - Photographs, 1990-2009 (Box 11)
  - Personal correspondence, 1971-2005 (Box 12)
  - Reviews of Girl in Movement, 2001 (Box 12)
  - Fragments, notes, and drafts, 1980-1999 (Box 12)
  - Typed journal, 2013-01-2013-06 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence and reviews regarding German publication of Girl in Movement, 2003 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1990-2010 (Box 13)